Finding Aid for Walter De Vries Papers, 1960-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Walter De Vries Papers
1960-2012
1960-1972
De Vries, Walter.
85147 Aa 2
Public opinion research pollster, aide to Michigan governor George Romney. Polling materials prepared for various Republican campaigns, notably the gubernatorial campaigns of George Romney in 1962 and 1966, Romney's campaign for president, 1967-1968, and the gubernatorial campaign of William Milliken, 1970; and polls conducted on state issues including detailed demographic information on the views of ethnic, religious, and racial minorities; also survey done for Senator Robert Griffin in 1971, and on attitude of state voters towards abortion in 1972. A small collection of material donated in 2013 is related to George Romney's son and the 2012 Republican presidential candidate, Mitt Romney.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
11 linear feet
The collection was the gift of Walter De Vries (donor no. 6354 ) and came to the library in 1979. Additional material was given by the donor in April 2013.
The collection is open to research.
Walter De Vries was born in 1929. After completing a one year business course at the Holland Business College he entered the armed forces in 1948. In 1949 he was discharged and enrolled in Hope College, but in 1951 he was recalled to active military duty. In 1954 De Vries received a bachelor's degree from Hope. In 1955 Michigan State University conferred upon him a master's degree, and in 1960 he obtained his doctorate, also from Michigan State.
While working on his doctorate De Vries taught at both Hope College and Calvin College and also served as a consultant regarding several public opinion surveys done within the state. Eventually he became a senior consultant for the Detroit-based Market Opinion Research firm.
In addition to his teaching and consultation, De Vries was very active in Republican politics. He first held party office in 1954, f when he was delegate from Holland's third ward to the Republican I County Convention. Throughout the 1950's he served in a number of party posts, including administrative assistant to the speaker of the Michigan House of Representatives from 1957 until 1961.
In 1961 De Vries was elected a delegate to the Michigan Constitutional Convention. There he became associated with George Romney. In 1962 he agreed to work as director of research for the Romney gubernatorial campaign. With Romney's victory, De Vries was appointed a special assistant to the governor-elect, and from 1963 until 1967 he served Romney as executive assistant for Program Development and Agency Liaison. In 1967 De Vries shifted responsibilities, working with Romney Associates, part of the Romney presidential effort. Subsequently De Vries assisted in the William Milliken gubernatorial campaign.
The papers of Walter De Vries reflect primarily his work for Romney and Milliken from 1962 until 1970. The papers are divided into two series, De Vries office files and polling data.
Subjects:
Abortion.; Demography.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Elections--Michigan--1966.; De Vries, Walter.; Elections--Michigan--1970.; Griffin, Robert P. (Robert Paul), 1923-2015; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Minorities--Michigan.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Republican Party (Mich.); Romney, Mitt.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Social surveys--Research.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1961-1963.
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Office material
  The office files are of limited value. They consist primarily of scattered items thought of lasting value, rather than a continuous flow of documents. Preserved among the items is a copy of John T. Dempsey's "Romney for Governor: The 1962 Michigan Election Campaign," a candid, unpublished manuscript written by an important campaign figure.
  - De Vries, Walter, "The Michigan Lobbyist: A Study in the Bases and Perceptions of Effectiveness" Ph.D. Thesis Michigan State University, 1960 (Box 1)
  - 1962
    - Dempsey, John T., "Romney for Governor: the Michigan Election Campaign" unpublished manuscript, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Market Opinion Research (Box 1)
    - Romney, George: memos (Box 1)
  - 1963
    - Market Opinion Research (Box 1)
    - Romney, George: memos (Box 1)
  - 1964
    - De Vries, Walter "General Evaluation and Progress Under the Romney Administration" (Box 1)
    - Republican Governors' Association (Box 1)
    - Republican Gubernatorial Candidates' Conference (Box 1)
    - Romney, George: memos (Box 1)
  - Romney, George: memos, 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966
    - De Vries Walter
      - "Outline of Remarks: Political Research" (Box 1)
      - Proponent (Box 1)
    - Market Opinion Research (Box 1)
    - "Role of the G.O.P." (Box 1)
    - Romney, George: memos (Box 1)
  - 1967
    - Kulsea, William C., "George Romney: The Angry Citizen" printed in the Grand Rapids Press (Box 1)
    - Market Opinion Research (Box 1)
    - Republican Governors' Association (Box 1)
    - Romney, George: memos (Box 1)
  - 1968
    - De Vries, Walter et. al. "What Makes Romney Run" and "The Computer's Function in Romney's Political Research" (Box 1)
    - Market Opinion Research, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Republican Governors' Association (Box 1)
  - 1969
    - Market Opinion Research
      - General (Box 1)
      - Proposal (Box 1)
    - Republican Governors' Association (Box 1)
  - 1970
    - Housing for Detroit (Proposition A) (Box 1)
    - Milliken, William
      - General (Box 1)
      - Government Reorganization, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Special messages (Box 1)
  - Milliken, William: special messages, 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972
    - Griffin, Robert (Box 1)
    - Milliken, William: special messages (Box 1)
- Polls: Data and analysis
  The polling data is the more interesting part of the collection. It covers a broader area than simple election statistics. There is a great deal of demographic information, particularly regarding ethnic, religious and racial minorities, and much detailed public opinion polling on major issues. Both the demographic and opinion data is often broken down to the precinct level. Along with the data is a great deal of analysis regarding what the numbers meant, and how best to utilize the information in various campaigns.
  The polling data can be divided into three sub-series, Romney material, Michigan material not related to Romney, and various outstate polls. Included in the collection is a detailed index to most of the Romney material. A few of Romney's national opinion polls, done for his presidential campaign, were not indexed. The Romney material is very rich, especially for the election of 1962. The non-Romney Michigan material consists primarily of work done for William Milliken, particularly his 1970 gubernatorial campaign. There is also a survey done for Robert Griffin in 1971 and a study regarding the attitude of state voters toward abortion in 1972. The outstate material consists of miscellaneous polls, many of which came to De Vries in his role as consultant for Market Opinion Research. Most extensive are the Bowles gubernatorial campaign in North Carolina, 1971-1972 and a national survey for the National Committee for a Human Life Amendment done in January 1975 and supplemented with a special analysis of Catholic respondents.
  - Romney polls (indexed)
    - Index (Box 2)
    - Binder 1
      - January 1956 (Box 2)
      - 1958 (Box 2)
      - Swainson-Hare poll, 1960 (Box 2)
      - 1960 (Box 2)
      - Analysis of spring elections, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Binder 2
      - Election statistics, 1954-1961 (Box 2)
    - Binder 3
      - Market Area Research project: Detroit and Wayne County, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Binder 4
      - County project: all Michigan counties, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Binder 5
      - Campaign schedules: Mr. and Mrs. Romney, May 28-November 6, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Binder 6
      - Issues including aging, agriculture, civil rights, conservation, constitutional convention, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Binder 7
      - Issues including fiscal structure, health and mental health, international trade, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Binder 8
      - Issues including crime and juvenile delinquency, economic growth, education, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Binder 9
      - Issues including labor and management, unemployment, upper peninsula, urban renewal, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Binder 10
      - "Romney on the Record:" position of Romney re. various issues of, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Binder 11
      - Pre-962 campaign material (Box 3)
      - Issue research (Box 3)
      - Poll, April 1962 (Box 3)
      - Semantics, April 1962 (Box 3)
      - Polling budget (Box 3)
      - Strategy research (Box 3)
      - Registration of voters (Box 3)
    - Binder 12, 1962
      - Romney volunteers (Box 3)
      - Campaign organization (Box 3)
      - Advance manual (Box 3)
      - Citizen questionnaire (Box 3)
      - Swainson record (Box 3)
    - Binder 13, 1962
      - Campaign techniques (Box 4)
      - Candidate impact study (Box 4)
      - Independents canvass (Box 4)
      - Apportionment study-media (Box 4)
      - Negro neighborhood study (Box 4)
      - Oak Park study (Box 4)
      - Primary data (Box 4)
      - Ethnic group location, Detroit (Box 4)
      - Romney-Nunn Audience study (Box 4)
      - In-Depth study, August 1962 (Box 4)
      - April-August comparison (Box 4)
      - Bentley-Staebler (Box 4)
    - Binder 14, 1962
      - Sound-on spots (Box 4)
      - T.V. scripts (Box 4)
      - General T.V. study, August 14 (Box 4)
      - T.V. debates, Detroit Standard Metropolitan Statistical Area (SMSA) and Muskegon County (Box 4)
      - Cuba Impact study, Detroit SMSA, October 25 (Box 4)
      - Harris schedule (Box 4)
      - Detroit News poll supplement, October 10-12 (Box 4)
    - Binder 15, 1962
      - Wayne County data, strategy (Box 4)
      - Weathervane precincts, Detroit, Hamtramck, Dearborn (Box 4)
      - Detroit News polls, January-November 1962 (Box 4)
      - November election (Box 4)
      - After-election study (Box 4)
      - Summary of After-election study (Box 4)
    - Binder 16, 1963
      - Con-Con after election study, 1962 (Box 4)
      - February Con-Con Study (Box 4)
      - February Study-Summary (Box 4)
      - Polling budget, 1963-1964 (Box 4)
      - June In-depth poll (Box 4)
      - June poll-analysis June poll-national (Box 4)
      - June poll-Semantics (Box 4)
      - Semantics, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
      - Ethnic breaks (Box 4)
    - Binder 17, 1964
      - Detroit Weathervane Precincts, analysis of gubernatorial vote, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Binder 18
      - Voter Profile, 1962-1963 (Box 5)
      - In-depth study, February 1964 (Box 5)
      - February analysis (Box 5)
    - Binder 19
      - In-depth study, May 1964 (Box 5)
      - Summary of May poll (Box 5)
    - Binder 20, 1964
      - Time, Techniques, Strategy memo (Box 5)
      - Heavyweight County voting analysis (Box 5)
      - Ticket splitting since, 1932 (Box 5)
      - Heavyweight counties ticket splitting (Box 5)
      - Marginal precinct study (Box 5)
      - Voter registration tabs (Box 5)
      - Registration drive (Box 5)
      - New voters (Box 5)
    - Binder 21, 1964
      - Campaign organization (Box 5)
      - Massachusetts ballot (Box 5)
      - February-May poll comparison (Box 5)
      - Primary election (Box 5)
      - Weathervane policy (Box 5)
      - Undecideds (Box 5)
      - Presidential and national (Box 5)
      - September poll summary (Box 5)
      - Radio spots test/T.V. (Box 5)
      - Civil rights, vote (Box 5)
      - Issues materials (Box 5)
      - Switch voters, 1962-1964 (Box 5)
      - Staebler vote analysis (Box 5)
      - U.S. Senate race (Box 5)
      - Detroit News polls (Box 5)
    - Binder 22, 1964
      - Election (Box 5)
      - After-election study (Box 5)
      - After-election Semantics (Box 5)
      - Independent voter cross-runs (Box 5)
      - After election analysis (Box 5)
    - Binder 23, 1964
      - Special CBS Election reports (Box 6)
    - Binder 24, 1965
      - November-December In-depth study (Box 6)
      - November-December Study-Semantics (Box 6)
      - 1961-1965 Comparison in-depth studies (Box 6)
    - Binder 25, 1966
      - Campaign organization (Box 6)
      - Computer runs (Box 6)
      - U.S. Senate race (Box 6)
      - U.S. Senate in-depth study Three county Detroit area (Box 6)
      - Test precinct study and analysis Ann Arbor, Monroe and Livonia (Box 6)
    - Binders 26-27 (Box 6)
      [not part of original accession]
    - Binder 28
      - Election Weathervanes, 1962; 1964; 1966 (Box 6)
    - Binder 29, National
      - Election night activities, 1966 (Box 6)
      - Election analyses, 1966 (Box 6)
      - General research memos (Box 6)
      - Domestic papers (Box 6)
      - Consultants (Box 6)
      - Organizational memos (Box 6)
    - Binder 30, National
      - Foreign policy research and strategy memo (Box 6)
      - Primary research and strategy (Box 6)
      - Convention research and strategy (Box 6)
      - Polling budget (Box 6)
      - Finance memos (Box 6)
      - Press and speech memos (Box 6)
    - Binder 31, National
      - In-depth poll, 1967 (Box 7)
      - In-depth analysis, 1967 (Box 7)
      - Regional breaks data, 1967 (Box 7)
      - Selected cross-runs/ballots, 1967 (Box 7)
    - Binder 32, National
      - In-depth semantic differentials, 1967 (Box 7)
      - In-depth semantics analysis, 1967 (Box 7)
      - County chairmen study, 1967 (Box 7)
      - New Hampshire in-depth summary, 1967 (Box 7)
      - Gallup-Harris polls trends (Box 7)
    - Binder 33, National
      - Presidential primaries, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Binder 34, National
      - Congressional district data (Box 7)
    - Binder 35, National
      - U.S. County data book (Box 7)
  - Romney regional presidential polls
    - East-North Central, 2 volumes (Box 7)
    - West North Central (Box 8)
    - Mid-Atlantic (Box 8)
    - West-South Central (Box 8)
    - Mountain (Box 8)
    - Pacific (Box 8)
    - U.S. total (Box 8)
  - Michigan polls
    - Statewide study of issues, legislature and candidates
      - January 1968 (Box 8)
    - Statewide aid to education study
      - March 1968 (Box 8)
    - Detroit area study for Michigan Association of Non-Public Schools, May 1969 (Box 9)
    - Milliken, 1970; 3 volumes
      - Test precincts data (Box 9)
      - May survey (Box 9)
      - Memos and correspondence (Box 9)
    - Television spot protests, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Griffin, 1971 (Box 10)
    - Abortion attitude study, 1972 (Box 10)
  - Outstate polls
    - Book 1, 1968-1969
      - Maine, First congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Massachusetts, Seventh congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Georgia, Fifth congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Minnesota statewide, 1968; 1969 (Box 10)
      - Ohio, Twenty-third congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Wisconsin, First congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
    - Book 2
      - Illinois, Third congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Illinois, Constitutional convention call, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Illinois, Republican state central committee, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Illinois, Post 1968 election study, 1969 (Box 10)
      - Indiana, Seventh congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Indiana, Third congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Indiana statewide, 1968 (Box 10)
    - Book 3
      - National study of republican county chairmen, 1967 (Box 10)
      - Jamaica discussion-simulation/reapportionment, 1968 (Box 10)
      - West Virginia, First congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - Pennsylvania, Sixth congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
      - New Jersey, Ninth congressional district, 1968 (Box 10)
    - Pennsylvania gubernatorial campaign, 1966 (Box 10)
    - Louisiana gubernatorial campaign, 1971; 2 volumes (Box 10)
    - North Carolina, 5 volumes
      - Voting behavior analysis, 1960-1968 (Box 11)
      - Survey of statewide political attitudes, August 1971 (Box 11)
      - Issues notebook Bowles gubernatorial campaign, 1971-1972 (Box 11)
      - Voter attitudes statewide, February 1972 (Box 11)
      - Post election analysis, Bowles campaign, May 1972 (Box 11)
    - National survey for national committee for a human life amendment, January 1975 (Box 11)
    - Special analysis of Catholic respondents, February 1975 (Box 11)
- Mitt Romney
  The Mitt Romney series is a small collection of material that was donated by De Vries separately in April 2013. Found here is material about Mitt Romney--George Romney's son--and his 2012 presidential campaign. Material includes De Vries' writings about George and Mitt Romney, correspondence, and collected articles about Mitt Romney's presidential campaign. Material is dated from 2006 to 2012.
  - Collected articles, 2010, 2012 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 2006, 2012 (Box 11)
  - Writings, 2007, 2012 (Box 11)